<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>His Highness Prince Rupert's letter to the Earl of Arlington, His Majesties principal secretary of state. from on board the Royal Charles off the oster-bank, the XXIXth of May, 1673. Distant from East Capel Seven Leagues, at one of the clock afternoon, the wind S.S.W.</title>
            <author>Rupert, Prince, Count Palatine, 1619-1682.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1673</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 5 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 3 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B05075</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing R2301</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R182889</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">52614903</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 52614903</idno>
            <idno type="VID">176069</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B05075)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 176069)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2761:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>His Highness Prince Rupert's letter to the Earl of Arlington, His Majesties principal secretary of state. from on board the Royal Charles off the oster-bank, the XXIXth of May, 1673. Distant from East Capel Seven Leagues, at one of the clock afternoon, the wind S.S.W.</title>
                  <author>Rupert, Prince, Count Palatine, 1619-1682.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>4 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Tho. Newcomb, ;</publisher>
                  <publisher>Reprinted by Andrew Anderson ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>In the Savoy :</pubPlace>
                  <pubPlace>Edinburgh, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1673.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Published by authority."</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: National Library of Scotland.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Arlington, Henry Bennet, --  Earl of, 1618-1685.</term>
               <term>Dutch War, 1672-1678 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Schooneveld, Battle of, 1673 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Restoration, 1660-1688 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:176069:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 27 -->
            <p>HIS HIGHNESS Prince Rupert's LETTER TO THE EARL OF <hi>ARLINGTON</hi> His Majeſties Principal Secretary of State. From on Board the <hi>ROYAL CHARLES</hi> off the <hi>Oſter-bank,</hi> the XXIX<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of <hi>May,</hi> 1673.</p>
            <p>Diſtant from <hi>Eaſt Capel</hi> Seven Leagues, at One of the Clock Afternoon, the Wind S. S. W.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Publiſhed by Authority.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the <hi>SAVOY:</hi> Printed by <hi>Tho. Newcomb.</hi> 1673.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> Reprinted by <hi>Andrew Anderſon,</hi> Printer to the King's moſt Excellent Majeſty. 1673.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:176069:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 28 -->
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:176069:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 28 -->
            <head>His Highneſs Prince <hi>Rupert's</hi> Letter to the Earl of <hi>Arlington,</hi> His Majesties Principal Secretary of State, from on' Board <hi>the Royal Charles</hi> off of the <hi>Oſter-bank,</hi> the <hi>29.</hi> of <hi>May, 1673.</hi> di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant from <hi>Eaſt Capel</hi> Seven Leagues, at one Afternoon, the Wind S. S. <hi>W.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Give you herein an account of our Action yeſterday, being the 28. ſuch as at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent can be made, having not had time to learn the Particulars of the Enemies loſſes. The foul weather before having given us opportunity and leiſure to ſound all the Sands; on the 27. It was reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved at a Council of War, held here on board with the Flag-Officers, to attack the Enemy riding at Anchor in a Line between the <hi>Rand</hi> and the <hi>Stony-bank.</hi> Accordingly a Squadron was then ordered out of the ſeveral Diviſions of the Fleet (whereof the Eldeſt Captain was to command each Party) conſiſting in all of 35. Frigats, and 13. Fire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips, beſides ſmal Craft to ſound before them. Yeſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day morning about 8. of the clock, they drew out of their Squadrons, and ſailed towards the Enemy, the Wind at <hi>S. S. W.</hi> and by 12. a Clock at Noon engaged the Van of them, commanded by <hi>Trump:</hi> We were forced to engage ſooner then I intended, to prevent the Enemies getting the Wind. That Squadron ſo commanded by <hi>Trump</hi> was ſo preſt by us, that it gave way, and retired as far as the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:176069:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 29 -->Sands would give them leave. The Squadron comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by <hi>De Ruyter</hi> fell to the ſhare of Count <hi>D' Estrées,</hi> and the <hi>French,</hi> who behaved themſelves very bravely. Sir <hi>Edward Spragge</hi> alſo on his ſide maintained the fight with ſo much courage and reſolution, that their whole body gave way to ſuch degree, that had it not been for fear of the Shoals, we had driven them into their har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bors, and the King would have had a better account of them. The caſe being thus, and the night approaching, I judged it fit to ſtand a little off, and to anchor here where I now ride.</p>
            <p>The enemy have had a conſiderable loſs (which they will not eaſily repair) having many men ſlain, many ſhips diſabled, and ſome deſtroyed; <hi>De Ruyter</hi> and <hi>Trump</hi> had run a great hazard of being burnt by ſome of our Fire-ſhips, if they had behaved themſelves as they ought to have done. Our loſſes are very inconſiderable, two of our Ships only being diſabled, <hi>viz.</hi> the <hi>Cambridge</hi> and the <hi>Reſolution,</hi> which I ſhal ſend home to refit, the reſt of our work will be eaſily done here. We have loſt very few Common Men; as yet I have an account but of theſe Officers ſlain; Captain <hi>Fowles,</hi> Captain <hi>Woerden,</hi> and Captain <hi>Finch</hi>) Colonel <hi>Hamiltoun</hi> hath his Leg ſhut off. All the Officers and Common Men, generally behaved themſelves very well, of which I ſhal ſend the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars, when I am better informed; In my Squadron more eſpecially Captain <hi>Leg,</hi> Sir <hi>John Holmes,</hi> Captain <hi>Wett<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wang,</hi> Captain <hi>Story,</hi> Sir <hi>Roger Strickland,</hi> and Sir <hi>William Reeves.</hi> The firſt took a Ship of the Enemies, and the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter brought up a Fire-ſhip, and laid himſelf to the Lee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward of <hi>Trump,</hi> and if the Captain of the Fire-ſhip had done his duty, <hi>Trump</hi> had certainly burnt; Notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding which, <hi>Story</hi> and <hi>Wittwang</hi> ſo belabored him, that <hi>Reeves</hi> cleared himſelf from the crowd of the Enemy. I hope His Majeſty will be ſatisfied, that conſidering the Place we engaged in, and the Sands, there was as much done as could be expected. And thus I leave it to His Majeſties Favorable Conſtruction, to whom I wiſh many happy Years to come, this being His Birth-day.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS:</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
